<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, France, and Ireland ... to all and singuler archbishops, bishops, archdecons, deanes and their officials ... know ye, that whereas the prisoners in the custodye of the marshall of the Marshalsey ...</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3781</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150968</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150968</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28840</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28840)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1874:99)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, France, and Ireland ... to all and singuler archbishops, bishops, archdecons, deanes and their officials ... know ye, that whereas the prisoners in the custodye of the marshall of the Marshalsey ...</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from STC (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Title information from first 9 lines of text.</note>
                  <note>For one-year collection for relief of prisoners in the Marshalsea.</note>
                  <note>"At our Mannor of Eastgreenwich the nine &amp; twentieth day of September, in the eight and thirteth [sic] yeere of our raigne."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marshalsea Prison (Southwark, London, England)</term>
               <term>Prisons --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28840:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Lizabeth by the grace of God, Queene of England, France, and Ireland defendor of the faith. &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>To all and ſinguler, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Arch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>decons, Deanes, and their Officials, Parſons, Vicars, Curates, and to all other ſpirituall perſsons: and alſo to all Juſtices of the peace, Maiors, Shirifes, Balifes, Conſtables, Churchwardens, and Sidemen: Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Miniſters and all other our faithfull Subiects within the Realme of England, as well within liberties as without, to whom theſe preſents ſhall come, greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Know ye, that whereas the Priſoners in the cuſtodye of the Marſhall of the Marſhalſey of our houſe, haue made to vs ſupplication that they haue not whereof to liue, neither any way be able to be comforted, but of ſuch deuout men to God and faithfull in Chriſt as are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling charitably to releeue them: we willing in this behalfe graciouſly to foreſee their pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, taking it to be a charitable act that ther may be yerely charity, we haue aſſigned our faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſubiect Hugh Oliuer by himſelf &amp; his ſufficient deputy, iointly or ſeueally to aſke, gather, receiue &amp; take, the almes, charity &amp; deuotion of our louing ſubiectes, inhabiting and dwelling within our County of Kent, with our Citties of Caunterbury and Rocheſter, and in our fiue Ports with, the members of the ſame, and in our Iſles of Tennet &amp; Sheppa: And the almes and gifts aforeſaid ſo by him or his deputy gathered and receiued, wel and faithfully to bring into our Court: &amp; yeeldan account therof, to our Warde or Keeyer or Clark of the ſame Priſon. As alſo to areſt &amp; attach aſwel al thoſe which by our licenſe as yet not obtained, do fame th<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues collectors of the ſaid almes, as alſo al thoſe which by any our letters to th<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e therof made, do gather the like rewards ouer &amp; aboue one yeer contrary to the tenor of the ſame our letters pattents. And thoſe ſo arreſted, to bring before our Marſhall whereſoeuer he ſhall then be in England, or to the Priſon of the Marſhalſey of our houſe aforeſaid lawfully to lead, there to remaine vntil they be puniſhed according to the law in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>Therefore we commaund you and euerye of you, that you gentlye receiue the aforeſaide Hugh Oliuer or his ſufficient deputy in this parte, to gather and receiue the almes and gifts aforeſaid, not doing or ſuffering to be done him or his deputye, anyhurt damage, moleſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or greefe: and if auyiniurye ſhall be done him or his deputy, that you doe amende the ſame without delay.</p>
            <p>Furthermore we commaund you the aforeſaid Conſtables, Church wardens &amp; officers, &amp; &amp; euery of you, that yot be counſailers &amp; helpers for the executing &amp; gathering of the premiſes. And alſo we commaund you the aforeſaid Parſons, Vicars and Curats, that you publiſh in pour Churches in your Pariſhes, he tenor of theſe preſents.</p>
            <p>In witnes whereof, we haue cauſed theſe our letters to be made pattents for the ſpace of one whole yeere to endure. Witnes George Carey Knight, Baron of Hunſdon, and great Marſhal of our houſe aforeſaid. At our Mannor of Caſtgreenwich the nine &amp; twenteth day of September, in the eight and thirteth yeere of our raigne.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
